Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov.
Today's דף daf is a new
פרק, perek, קז, kuf zayin, פרק בית שמאי, Perek Beit Shammai, although
the פרק perek doesn't focus on בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, but anyway
it certainly משנה Mishnah opens with a series of debates of בית
שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל Beit Hillel and we're back to
the land of יבום. yibbum. So let's take a look. All right,
בית שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai omrim, בית שמאי Beit Shammai says, אין
ממאנין אלא ארוסות, ein mema'anin ela arusot, מיאון, mi'un, I mean when
it's a sort of not יבום yibbum per se, but will soon
intersect with יבום, yibbum, but right now we're in the world but
right now we're dealing with מיאון. mi'un. You'll remember מיאון mi'un about
a girl whose father died קז kuf zayin 107 whose father died
and brothers and mother married her off. We'll find out in a
minute that when they marry her off even though she's under age,
it's מדעתה, mi-da'atah, she actually agrees to the marriage. That's important because
the גמרא Gemara will sort of introduce or address that fact. Anyway,
her mother and brothers marry her off and she is until she
becomes an adult, she is allowed to be ממאן, mema'en, refuse her
husband. Okay, and then so there's going to be questions now of
exactly at what stage can she refuse her husband, number one, be
ממאן mema'en and walk away, and when she is ממאן mema'en the
effect it has is that she is retroactively considered never to have
been married. It's not like a גט, get, you know, where she
was married and now she's free, which it have let's say implications
for כהונה kehunah or something of that sort. No, retroactively it's like
she was never married. That's מיאון. mi'un. So we're going to deal
with what stages under what circumstances she can and can't do that,
and then we're also going to deal with its implications for יבום.
yibbum. So let's take a look again. בית שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai
omrim, אין ממאנין אלא ארוסות. ein mema'anin ela arusot.
Only the women who are ארוסות, arusot, these young girls, while they're
still in the ארוסה arusa stage can they do מיאון, mi'un, but
once they've actually been נשואות, nesuot, started living with their husbands, being
having sex and living with their husbands, they can no longer do
מיאון. mi'un. Obviously the marriage has reached a much different level when
it has become not just, you know, technical and legal but actually
a lived reality. ובית הלל אומרים u'Beit Hillel omrim and בית הלל
Beit Hillel says, ארוסות ונשואות. arusot unesout.
At either stage, either the ארוסה arusa or the נשואה nesua stage
she can still do מיאון. mi'un. בית שמאי אומרים, בבעל Beit Shammai
omrim b'ba'al. ולא ביבם. bi-yavam,
She can only do יבום... yibbum... מיאון mi'un against her husband, refuse
her husband, not the brother-in-law. Now what is this scenario in which
she would do מיאון mi'un to her brother-in-law? The scenario is is
that she had this marriage to a man by her mother and
brothers, so it was only rabbinic, it was not biblical, and then
her husband died, the man that she could have done מיאון mi'un
to thank you so much died, and then the and now she
has his guy his brother and she has a מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibbum and חליצה. chalitzah. Can מיאון mi'un be effective at this
stage? And there'll be different scenarios of that. So בית שמאי Beit
Shammai says no she cannot, ובית הלל אומרים u'Beit Hillel omrim and
בית הלל Beit Hillel says, בבעל וביבם be-ba'al u-be-yabam she can do
מיאון mi'un whether to the husband or to the brother-in-law. בית שמאי
אומרים בפניו, Beit Shammai omrim befanav,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says the מיאון mi'un has to be in
the presence of the man, of the husband. ובית הלל אומרים בפניו
ושלא בפניו u'Beit Hillel omrim befanav veshelo befanav in his presence and
not in his presence. בית שמאי אומרים בבית דין, Beit Shammai omrim
be-Beit Din, it has to be in the presence of a court.
ובית הלל אומרים בבית דין ושלא בבית דין, u'Beit Hillel omrim be-Beit
Din veshelo be-Beit Din, it doesn't have to be in the presence
of a court. אמרו להן בית הלל לבית שמאי, Amru lahen Beit
Hillel le-Beit Shammai, so בית הלל Beit Hillel said to בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, ממאנת וקטנה אפילו ארבע וחמש פעמים. mema'enet u-ketanah afilu arba
va-chamesh pe'amim.
It's interesting אמרו להם amru lahem because you expect an argument when
it's אמרו להם, amru lahem, whereas here it's really just a הלכה
halakhic statement. A woman can be ממאן mema'en as a minor even
four or five times. ממאנת mema'enet with one guy, then the brother
and mother marry off to another guy, ממאנת mema'enet with another guy,
then brother and mother marry off from ממאנת mema'enet with an next
guy, so בית הלל Beit Hillel says we would allow that multiple
times. אמרו להם בית שמאי Amru lahem Beit Shammai to which בית
שמאי Beit Shammai responded, אין בנות ישראל הפקר. ein benot Yisrael hefker.
You cannot treat daughters of ישראל Yisrael as הפקר, hefker, as like
unprotected ownerless, basically, you know, handed over from one man to the
next, I mean it's her choice, but nevertheless, it makes her considered
to be like, you know, treated you know, treated in a way
that objectified, true, right, objectified and just basically not treated in a
way that respects you know that is protective of her status. אלא,
ella, one minute, אלא ממאנת ella mema'enet
so if she want to be ממאנת mema'enet with the first guy
she could be, but after she's ממאנת mema'enet with the first guy,
ממתנת עד שתגדיל, mamtenet ad shetagdil,
she waits till she becomes an adult, ותמאן ותינשא, ve-tema'en ve-tinase, and
then she does מיאון mi'un and she marries, meaning don't go ahead
and marry the next guy because if you marry another guy as
a קטנה, ketanah, you might do מיאון mi'un again. So if you
did מיאון mi'un with the first guy, then wait till you become
an adult to get married for the second time. Now the question
is why it says תמאן tema'en a second time, just says wait
to become an adult and get married for the second time, so
the גמרא Gemara is going to deal with what the meaning of
that statement is, why it throws in the word
תמאן tema'en there. Yes, I
guess there's gotta be... It's a good question like I haven't actually
paid attention to that when it's the type of a exchange, אמרו
להם, amru lahem, אמרו להם amru lahem etc, does בית הלל Beit
Hillel come regularly first or בית שמאי Beit Shammai or maybe it
sort of matters you know case by case. Right here בית שמאי
Beit Shammai is saying the claim that has to come second, I
mean if somebody starts by saying you can't allow the בנות ישראל
Bnot Yisrael to be treated as הפקר, hefker, that's in reaction to
a statement that I'm going to allow her to marry four or
five times so it actually obviously has to come second because it
has to be reacting to the statement of
בית הלל. Beit Hillel.
Yeah, I'm sorry, Jonathan, my head isn't working today. It's all in
context of where the girl who doesn't have a choice? That last
injunction is directed towards her mother and brother, isn't it? Right,
that's true, you're right. So and but it's interesting because she actually
does have a choice in terms of the next you know we're
going to see in the גמרא Gemara that you can only marry
her off in this scenario לדעתה le-da'atah when her father marries her
off it could even be שלא לדעתה she-lo le-da'atah but you're right,
this is not even an injunction it's like just a legal restriction
meaning because of the concern of לא יהיו בנות ישראל הפקר lo
yehei Bnot Yisrael hefker we prevent we don't allow it to even
be binding the next time. The question not clear in the משנה
mishna is can they marry her second time without the opportunity of
מיאון, mi'un, you know which in a way is like
even robbing her of a certain amount of freedom and control within
the context of לא יהיו בנות ישראל הפקר, lo yehei Bnot Yisrael
hefker, but you're right the focus shifts and we're going to see
in the גמרא Gemara exactly how that plays out. Michael. So I
don't understand why it sounds like she has to do מיאון mi'un
twice to the same person. Yeah, so that's what I said. The
גמרא Gemara is going to discuss that, yeah. But also like you
know this reminds me of the same thing in שביעית פרק ז'
משנה ח', Shevi'it Perek Zayin Mishna Chet, right you know
with the הכישתה לאמה hakhishat le-amah like you know the point purpose
is supposed to be marrying her and then not and then like
you know you can't give her to some give her right, right,
right אחרי אשר הוטמאה akharei asher huttama'ah right, right, right what's that
right there too?
That's a nice point. Right, you're right that actually is exactly about
a קטנה ketanah and the whole point of it's a very excellent
point that the whole idea לא יהיו בנות ישראל הפקר lo yehei
Bnot Yisrael hefker is like look, you know there's certain opportunities here
but if you sort of keep on doing it again and again
then you're right you're treating her like a piece of like garbage
or whatever some type of an object that can be passed around
and that's you know and that's not in her interest. So you're
right it is very much like that like the פסוקים psukim there.
Yes, just very simply so what do the parents do to the
קטנה ketanah is קידושין? kiddushin? Not parents, mother and brother. Yeah, they
marry her off there's קידושין kiddushin and then she starts living with
the guy and that's נישואין, nisu'in, maybe they have a חופה chuppah
even and a wedding and they send out embossed invitations, yeah.
Like the little
footprints. Exactly, exactly. Maybe they have some sort of I know it's
rabbinic but usually they pin this on some sort of verse so
they can do that you know what I mean like where... No,
I don't know maybe but clearly it's rabbinic. Okay, let's look at
the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Shmuel, מאי טעמא דבית שמאי Mai ta'ama de-Beit Shammai now we're going
to look at all these interesting debates of בית שמאי Beit Shammai
and בית הלל. Beit Hillel. מאי טעמא דבית שמאי, Mai ta'ama de-Beit
Shammai, what's the reasoning of the first position of בית שמאי Beit
Shammai that once the girl is נשואה nisu'ah she can no longer
do
מיאון. mi'un. לפי שאין תנאי בנישואין Lefi she-ein tnai be-nisu'in because we
start with the assumption that once in a normal you know like
a דאורייתא de-oraita marriage there's קידושין kiddushin and נישואין nisu'in and even
if you could make stipulations by the קידושין kiddushin once you reach
the stage of נישואין nisu'in the stipulations would no longer work. I'll
get back to that statement in a minute. So therefore after in
a normal marriage after נישואין nisu'in there's no way you could say
oh because of this stipulation retroactively the marriage never took place. By
the way, just to say parenthetically that doesn't mean there can't be
a sense of קידושי טעות, kiddushei ta'ut, meaning if there was an
actual error you know like oh my god I thought you were
this and actually turns out you were that right and then it's
not a stipulation it's something that is fundamental to why the person
engaged in the basic you know transaction or marriage itself, that can
retrospectively nullify a marriage even at the stage of נישואין. nisu'in. But
if it's an external
stipulation, על מנת ש... al mnat she... that type of external type
of a concern and stipulation is no longer meaningful after נישואין. nisu'in.
I'll discuss that in a minute. And therefore in a normal marriage
there would be no normal way after they were נישואין nisu'in that
then the marriage could retroactively be dissolved. Again, parenthetically except for the
case of טעות ta'ut but in terms of case of תנאי tnai
certainly not. And therefore because that's the case, ואם נשואה תמאן ve-im
nisu'ah tema'en and if you let this girl who's a נשואה nisu'ah
do מיאון, mi'un, אתי למימר ati l-meimar so people will see they've
been living together for three years and then all of a sudden
she walked away without a גט. get. What's the explanation? It must
be that there was some stipulation and they'll think that a תנאי
tnai works in נישואין. nisu'in. ואם נשואה תמאן אתי למימר יש תנאי
בנישואין, Ve-im nisu'ah tema'en ati l-meimar yesh tnai be-nisu'in,
people will think that there was the reason that she walked away
was there was a תנאי tnai and therefore that'll lead to bad
things because because then people will assume that they can make stipulations
and walk away from marriages even when it's an adult woman getting
married, because they'll think that תנאים tenaim work by נישואין, nisuin, and
therefore we can't allow this to happen because this sort of violates
certain norms and certain impressions
about when can a person, whether a person could walk away from
נישואין nisuin without a גט. get. And they'll think if it can
happen here, it can happen in other marriages as well with a
condition. Now, this idea of אין תנאי בנישואין, ein tenai benisuin, right,
is very important because what's first of all the reason? The general
reason is that the assumption is that it's not like objectively it's
impossible. The גמרא Gemara says the reason that would be true is
because אין אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות, ein adam oseh beilato beilat
zenut, that once they started living together and having sex, the person
doesn't want to say, oh, well, you know, if it works out
that this condition isn't met, retroactively we were never married and therefore
we're having sex here outside of marriage. That would be considered בעילת
זנות, beilat zenut, and therefore if there were any condition, they would
basically waive it in order because they wouldn't want once they're starting
to have sex with one another, they wouldn't want that to be
conditional or the status of that held in abeyance. So therefore any
possible stipulation they would have automatically waived. So that is not an
objective statement that תנאי tenai is impossible. It just says that as
a general rule, we assume that תנאים tenaim were sort of waived
at that time. Now that's important because a lot of the whole,
one of the approaches dealing with the עגונה agunah situation is to
make a תנאי, tenai, right, this already came up with the rabbis
in France in the mid-19th century, and then the big opposition came
to it and there was a whole ספר sefer which was printed,
which was a collection of all of these sort of rabbinic responses
that attacked this as a way of dealing with the עגונה, agunah,
and the name of the ספר sefer was אין תנאי בנישואין. Ein
Tenai BeNisuin.
But again, there are some arguments that it's not, that maybe under
certain conditions it could work. It's not an absolute. And if you
by the way just look at the little תוספות Tosafot here, תוספות
Tosafot says,
אמר דבית שמאי אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מאי טעמא דבית שמאי
לפי שאין תנאי בנישואין תימה דבפרק המדיר גבי קידשה על תנאי וכנסה
סתם קאמר שמואל דאינה צריכה גט ומוקי לה אביי ורבא כבית שמאי
דמפרש טעמא דבית שמאי שאין אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות אלמא אפילו
בבית שמאי לשמואל יש תנאי בנישואין ובית הלל נמי וכו'. Amara d'Beit
Shammai Amara Rav Yehudah amar Shmuel mai ta'ama d'Beit Shammai lefi she'ein
tenai benisuin teimah deperek HaMadir gabei kidshah al tenai vekhansah stam ka'amar
Shmuel de'einah tzerikhah get umoki lah Abaye veRava keBeit Shammai demefaresh ta'ama
d'Beit Shammai she'ein adam oseh beilato beilat zenut alma afilu beBeit Shammai
leShmuel yesh tenai benisuin uBeit Hillel nami etc. etc.. So he basically
quotes a whole other סוגיא sugya where the same שמואל Shmuel here,
who explains the reason based on the background of אין תנאי בנישואין
ein tenai benisuin in the גמרא Gemara in כתובות, Ketubot, holds יש
תנאי בנישואין. yesh tenai benisuin. Okay. And then he sort of works
through the answer. But what I wanted you to just see is
something that's presented here as absolute. Number one is that it's not
based on, like I said, legally it's not possible, it's based on
the assumption that it's waived. And number two, in other סוגיות, sugyos,
they take opposite positions, even שמואל Shmuel himself takes an opposite position.
Okay, so back to the גמרא. Gemara. So that's one reason. Reason
is because it looks like people will misinterpret this as a תנאי,
tenai, and that'll lead to error in law. So the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, so let's read that again, ואי נישואין אתא למיעיין אתי
למימר יש תנאי בנישואין. ve'i nisuin ata lema'ein ati lemeimar yesh tenai
benisuin. נכנסה לחופה, nichnesah lechuppah, says the גמרא, Gemara, let's say she
just had a חופה, chuppah, she hasn't yet, they haven't yet had
sex, ולא נבעלה, velo nivalah, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? Why
should she not be able to do מיאון miun there? Now how
do you know she can't do מיאון miun there? Because רש"י Rashi
points out, it doesn't say בית שמאי Beit Shammai says אין נשואה
ein nisuah cannot do מיאון. miun.
Then maybe you could do מיאון miun once it's נכנסה לחופה. nichnesah
lechuppah.
They don't say a נשואה nisuah cannot. What do בית שמאי Beit
Shammai say? Only an ארוסה arusah can. Right? This is something that
the sort of point of the excluded middle. The problem is that
people, when you sort of explain things, the difference
between, the difference of A is not the. The difference of vanilla
is not chocolate. The difference of A is not A. The difference
of vanilla is not vanilla. Like if you want to include the
whole world of things. So when you have נשואה nisuah and ארוסה,
arusah, there's a gap in between. So halakhically, it's a difference between
saying only an ארוסה arusah can, and saying a נשואה nisuah cannot.
The difference is anybody in between those two statuses. Right? So that's
what the גמרא Gemara assumes. Since בית שמאי Beit Shammai says only
an ארוסה arusah can, anybody who's not an ארוסה, arusah, even if
they're not yet at the נשואה nisuah stage, cannot. Who's somebody that's
not an ארוסה arusah but not yet at the נשואה nisuah stage?
חופה. chuppah. Okay, we might call that נשואה, nisuah, but anyway in
the גמרא, Gemara, it's not a full נשואה nisuah because she hasn't
had sex. Now the גמרא Gemara assumes that the whole reason you
don't have a תנאי בנישואין tenai benisuin is because you don't want
your act of sex to be, sort of, its context to be
uncertain. But here you haven't had sex yet, you're just having חופה,
chuppah, so maybe a תנאי tenai should work for חופה. chuppah. And
if a תנאי tenai could work for
חופה, chuppah, then מיאון miun should be able to work for, after
חופה, chuppah, before sex. Okay? So that's what the גמרא Gemara's question
is. So why not, why can't you do מיאון miun after חופה?
chuppah? Because תנאי tenai should be able to work for that. So
the גמרא Gemara says, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? So the
גמרא Gemara says, לפי שאין תנאי בחופה, lefi she'ein tenai bechuppah, okay,
without explaining why, no, תנאי tenai won't work for חופה chuppah either,
because since חופה chuppah is... But like in the context of sex,
you would not want even your חופה chuppah *Chuppah* to have been
in a context, because חופה chuppah *Chuppah* suggests sex. The whole idea
of חופה chuppah *Chuppah* is that you're now going to start living
together, it's sort of the house, it's about, you know, the idea
of being private and so on. So even that you would not
have to want retroactively to have been in a context which it
was not a real, you know, marriage context. So you wouldn't want
a תנאי tnai *tnai* to work for חופה chuppah *Chuppah* either. You'd
want to be מוחה *mocheh* your תנאי *tnai* for חופה chuppah *Chuppah*
as well. So since there's no תנאי *tnai* for חופה chuppah *Chuppah*,
there's also going to be no מיאון mi'un *mi'un* after חופה chuppah?
*Chuppah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, okay, but there's another stage
even before חופה chuppah *Chuppah* that the woman is no longer ארוסה
*arusa*. What's that stage? מסר אב לשלוחי הבעל מה איכא למימר *Masar
av l'shluchei haba'al mai ika l'maimar*. What happens if the father gives
the woman over to the husband's שלוחים *shluchim*, right? In a case
where we really are talking about a minor that the father married
off, רש״י *Rashi* points out we're not talking about father here, right?
Because the whole point here is there's no father, that's why you
have this whole scenario. But that's right you're not right but in
a standard case right the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* imagines the following that,
you know, the father marries off his minor daughter and this is
משניות *Mishnayot* in כתובות *Ketubot*, then the husband sends over his messengers
to collect the goods, to collect the daughter. The father gives her
over to the שלוחים *shluchim* and the messengers go bring her back
to the husband's house. So at that moment when she leaves the
father's house but has not yet entered into the husband's house, right,
the whole idea is a transition from father's house to husband's house
that happens at the time of נישואין nisu'in, *nissu'in*. So in that
handing over before she's left the father's house but hasn't yet come
to the husband, she's no longer in the pure ארוסה *arusa* state
but she's not yet at the נשואה *nesua* state either. She hasn't
had חופה *Chuppah*, she hasn't had ביאה biah? *bi'ah*, she's in this
middle state. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says if that you
would have a similar scenario without the father but with the mother
and the brothers, right? So she's no longer ארוסה *arusa*. Why can't
she do מיאון mi'un. *mi'un*? Okay, because presumably a תנאי *tnai* would
still be effective here. They haven't even had that intimacy or that
suggested intimacy of the חופה *Chuppah*. So presumably a תנאי *tnai* should
work here and if תנאי *tnai* could work in this stage, then
מיאון mi'un *mi'un* should work in this stage. So the normal cases
of where מיאון mi'un *mi'un* apply, when
when a parent marries off the minor daughter, she doesn't normally stay
in the father's house and wait until she's older? She does. But
when the קידושין kiddushin? *kiddushin* becomes moving into the נישואין nisu'in. *nissu'in*,
then the next day, oh you mean when did they actually start
the נישואין nisu'in. *nissu'in*, did they wait till she's an adult or
not? Yeah, clear for, you would like to think so, but it's
not true, at least not in all the cases. Right, I know,
I know, believe me, believe me, I get it. Okay, for my
norms we'd like to imagine that maybe the קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin* happens
as a minor, but they actually only start living together after she's
an adult, no, I mean maybe sometimes but certainly you can't assume
that that's the case. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. Okay, so מסר אב לשלוחי הבעל מה איכא למימר *Masar av
l'shluchei haba'al mai ika l'maimar*? What if it's again even before חופה
*Chuppah* but she's out of the father's house so she's no longer
a pure ארוסה *arusa* or out of the mother's house? So if
that since the תנאי *tnai* should presumably will work there, why can't
מיאון mi'un *mi'un* work there? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no,
לא פלוג רבנן lo plug rabanan. *lo plug rabanan*. You're right, a
תנאי *tnai* could work there but once we're saying we don't want
her to do מיאון mi'un *mi'un*, you know, after when she stops
being an ארוסה *arusa*, we're not going to distinguish between these subtle
gradations of you know between ארוסה *arusa* and נשואה *nesua*. Once she
stops being an ארוסה *arusa* she can't because it's all connected to
the idea of נישואין *nissu'in*. Okay, so you're right, not every case
exactly works, but nevertheless we don't want it because it makes people
think that a woman could walk away from נישואין *nissu'in* without a
גט get. *get* and they'll think that there is a תנאי בנישואין
*tnai b'nissu'in*. Okay, okay, ובית הלל u-Beit Hillel *v'Beit Hillel*, now what's
בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beit Hillel*'s response to this? מידי ידיע דנישואי
קטנה ketana? דרבנן derabbanan, נינהו *midei yedia d'nissu'ei ktanah d'rabanan ninhu*. People
will not make a mistake, they'll realize she's a minor. Now and
therefore it's all rabbinic, it's only all rabbinic because there's also no
father but okay. They'll realize that a minor without a father is
all rabbinic, they'll understand it's a special case and just because they
see this young girl, this you know underage girl, walk away, they're
not going to make any assumptions about תנאי בנישואין *tnai b'nissu'in*. So
that's one way of understanding it, but what it will do with
our impressions about תנאי בנישואין *tnai b'nissu'in*. That's explanation number one. רבה
ורב יוסף דאמרי תרוייהו *Rabba v'Rav Yosef d'amrei tarvaihu*, here's explanation number
two of בית שמאי Beit Shammai. *Beit Shammai*. רבה ורב יוסף *Rabba
v'Rav Yosef* both say, טעמא דבית שמאי לפי שאין אדם עושה בעילתו
בעילת זנות *ta'ama d'Beit Shammai lefi she'ein adam oseh be'ilato be'ilat znut*.
A man does not make his acts of sex into acts of,
you know, fornication. That's what we said before underlay the principle of
אין תנאי בנישואין ein tnai b'nisuin *ein tnai b'nissu'in*. But here we're
saying it more immediately, not about a concern about what impressions will
be, about the actual reality of this marriage. What's going to happen?
This man is going to start living with this girl. I mean
of course we would say it's more than בעילת זנות *be'ilat znut*,
for us it would seem like, you know, it would basically we
would treat it as rape, you know, we would treat it as
like child abuse, having sex with a girl under 12 years old.
But again, those were the realities in the time of the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. So he's going to start living with this young girl
and having sex with her and you're going to tell him, oh
you know even though you're having sex with her, at any day
she can wake up and do מיאון mi'un, *mi'un* and walk away.
So he's going to say, whoa I don't want to do that,
I don't want to start, you know, having an intimate sexual relationship...
relationship with a woman who might be able to redefine it as
though she wasn't my wife. I only want to do it in
the context of marriage. Okay, so because that would basically make people
not want to go to the stage of נשואין Nisuin and presumably
now why didn't you say okay big deal so don't do נשואין
Nisuin. if it's going to bother you wait until she becomes an
adult. Okay, so but the point being that clearly because the rabbis
created the reality of קידושי קטנה Kidushi Ketana when there's no father
it reflects the fact about the father being able to provide for
his kids and you marry the daughter off even at a young
age and she's provided for and there were very clear economic societal
needs for this institution. So therefore you wanted people if there were
those needs you wanted it to be actually translated into נשואין. Nisuin
You don't want the guy to say okay I'll do it but
then I'm not going to take care of her. You want to
start living with her and providing for her taking care of her
you want it to move on to נשואין Nisuin and therefore if
you're going to say she can walk away and do מיאון mi'un
it's not the guy's not going to want to do נשואין nisuin.
because he's not going to want to have this act of the
marital sex become non-marital sex because she decided that she's walking away.
Okay so that's why we don't allow מיאון. mi'un לפי שאינה דומה
ביאה לביאה וניסוין לניסוין. Lefi she-eina doma bi'a l'bi'a v'nisuin l'nisuin. So
the גמרא Gemara says the same קושיא kushya בנכנסה לחופה ולא נבעלה
מה איכא למימר. v'nichnesa l'chuppah v'lo niv'ala mah ika l'meimar. So how
about why can't she do מיאון mi'un though after the חופה before
sex? Says the גמרא Gemara לא ניחא ליה דתהוי חופת איסורא. lo
nicha lei d'teihavei chuppat issura. Similar like we said before about why
there's no תנאי בחופה b'chuppah the גמרא Gemara is assuming he doesn't
want this act of חופה retroactively to be I was having חופה
with a woman who never wound up being my wife. Again חופה
is suggestive of the whole idea of the intimacy and the living
together etc. so you don't want same way we don't want the
sex to have been extra non-marital sex you don't want the חופה
to have been a חופה in a non-marital context. חופת איסורא. chuppat
issura. מסרה לשלוחי האב מה איכא למימר. masra lishluchei ha-av mah ika
l'meimar. Okay why can't she at least do מיאון mi'un though in
this scenario where she was handed over to his representatives even before
חופה? There there should be no problem if it's retroactively turns out
to be nothing so let her do מיאון mi'un there. So לא
פלוג lo plug. רבנן. All right that already is a לא פלוג.
So the nice thing about this next stage is it takes the
what was the concern of impressions of אין תנאי בנישואין which was
informed by a concern of אינה דומה ביאה לביאה וניסוין לניסוין eina
doma bi'a l'bi'a v'nisuin l'nisuin and makes it less of a concern
of impressions and other than more of a concern about the very
relationship itself and the reality of the relationship you don't want that
to be redefined that you were having sex or חופה the man
would with a woman who wound up not being his wife. Yes
Dov. So the כתובה ketubah is given at the time of the
קידושין? kiddushin We write the כתובה ketubah at the time of the
קידושין. kiddushin The real the real כתובה ketubah begins at the time
of the נשואין. nisuin Yeah but but here it's like give you
take קידושין kiddushin כתובה ketubah but not נשואין nisuin yet. Oh we
didn't read בית הלל Beit Hillel yet. Wait let me read בית
הלל Beit Hillel's then you can ask your question. Okay so that's
בית שמאי. So the גמרא Gemara says ובית הלל בית הלל's Beit
Hillel response would be כיון דאיכא קידושין וכתובה לא אתו למימר דביאתו
ביאת זנות. keivan d'ika kiddushin v'ketubah lo atu l'meimar d'biato biat zenut.
Since when they are married it's taking place in the context of
קידושין kiddushin and כתובה ketubah meaning at the נשואין nisuin once it
gets to נשואין right what בית הלל Beit Hillel? is saying is
look retroactively she's not considered married but at the time it was
not just סתם stam you guys were sleeping around. It was done
in the context of a rabbinic institution and that was a rabbinic
framework was preceded with an act of קידושין kiddushin it was preceded
with a כתובה ketubah then you started living together. So you had
these concrete things. It wasn't two people took out a hotel room.
You had קידושין kiddushin. you had כתובה ketubah and so on. So
therefore even if הלכתית halachically retroactively she is it was not קידושין
kiddushin. and it was not a marriage it never it doesn't have
that experience it won't be framed as a ביאת זנות. biat zenut.
By the way that's an interesting point because well first of all
there's two points. Number one is הלכתית halachically right it may that's
very important because retroactively if she does מיאון mi'un how do we
look at this at the minor? Like do we say oh this
is a girl who had sex outside of marriage for whatever הלכה
halacha that might be relevant? Not for כהן kohen you might need
to be חלוצה chalutza or גרושה gerusha or whatever but there is
the idea there are opinions for example in the גמרא Gemara that
a זונה zonah for a כהן kohen is any woman who's had
sex outside of marriage. Would you look at this girl this way?
The answer is no. Even if technically we say it uproots legally
the marriage at the same time we don't say that the marriage
was extramarital or that the sex was extramarital sex. She was never
married but the sex which took at its time took place in
the context of this rabbinic institution will never be extramarital sex. But
let me ask you even a simpler question. רמב"ם Rambam is of
the position that any sex outside of marriage is an איסור דאורייתא
issur d'oraita is a לאו דאורייתא lav d'oraita of לא תהיה קדשה
lo tihyeh kedeishah of not being a prostitute. רמב"ם Rambam says that
any sex outside of marriage is considered like a prostitute. It's not
for hire, it's sex not in the context of marriage.
A דאורייתא d'oraita איסור. issur. Okay so the question is according to
the רמב"ם Rambam how did they let this man and woman, this
girl... ...you know, in this rabbinic institution, it's sex outside of marriage.
הלכה halachah. דאורייתא de'oraisa *Halacha d'Oraisa*, it's not קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*; it's
only a rabbinic institution. How did the rabbis ever allow for rabbinic
marriages, which are not דאורייתא de'oraisa *d'Oraisa* marriages? Why isn't it always
a violation of the איסור דאורייתא de'oraisa *issur d'Oraisa* of sex outside
of marriage according to the רמב"ם *Rambam*? And the answer is because
it's not outside of marriage. Even though it's not a legally married,
you know, legally דאורייתא de-Oraisa *d'Oraisa* marriage, because it's within the institution
of marriage and within at least a rabbinic legal system marriage, that's
enough to redefine the nature of the sex. And we're no longer
talking about זנות *znut* because it's taking place within this rabbinic institution,
within these clear realities of קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* and so on. And
that remains true even if retroactively the girl undermines it; it's not
going to redefine the nature of the sex. It's also very interesting
because in the issues I raised before, the עגונה *agunah* questions and
אין אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות *ein adam oseh beilato beilat znut*,
some you know, some contemporary פוסקים *poskim* have said that nowadays even
if the marriage isn't binding halachically, but the couple is still like
married according to... meaning even though אין תנאי בנישואין *ein tnai b'nisuin*,
and why wouldn't you want there to be a תנאי בנישואין *tnai
b'nisuin*? Because it would make the ביאה biah *biah* to be a
בעילת זנות *beilat znut*. So some want to say, "But yeah, but
nowadays, you know, it's not because you're still living within the context
of a secular law marriage, and you're still living right?" And therefore,
it would not be defined as בעילת זנות *beilat znut*, even if
it's not halachically קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*, is the institution of secular law
marriage enough to say that it's not בעילת זנות *beilat znut*, right?
It's a very good question. It's similar to this, even if retroactively
it's not legally, A, it's only rabbinic, B, retroactively it was dissolved,
nevertheless, it wasn't בעילת זנות *beilat znut* because that wasn't the reality
of how it was taking place. That then leads to a similar
question extended even further on that continuum. I mean, a couple moves
in with each other, you know, they're out of college, they're boyfriend
and girlfriend. You think that applies today? אין אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת
זנות *ein adam oseh beilato beilat znut*? So that's a different question
when it's like a living relationship and a committed relationship, but it
has no sort of a legal structure, no framework, etc. Right? That's
already taking it to another level. But this case it has, it
had a קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*, it had a כתובה *ketubah* and so
on. What about the case of the כתובה *ketubah* if she does
מיאון mi'un *miun*? Right, so then she doesn't collect her כתובה *ketubah*.
Right, exactly. We're going to get... the next thing is going to
start addressing some of the כתובה *ketubah* issues. Let's take a look.
רב Rav, פפא אמר *Rav Pappa amar* טעמא דבית שמאי משום פירי
*taama d'Beis Shammai mishum peiri*, טעמא דבית הלל משום פירי *taama d'Beis
Hillel mishum peiri*. Both of them, it's financial issues that are at
stake. The fruit, remember נכסי מלוג *nichsei milug*, the property she brings
in that she retains title to but he has a right to
benefit from. So what's at stake here? Let's take... and that only
happens at the time of נישואין *nisuin*. So טעמא דבית שמאי משום
פירי *taama d'Beis Shammai mishum peiri*, דאמרת נשואה תמאן *d'amart nisuah tmaen*,
if she's going to... you're going to tell her that she can
be ממאן mema'en *memaen*, so שמא יאכיל להו מיניה *shami d'achil lehu
minei*, he's going to sort of sneak away, secret away and eat
the fruit from the field without like investing in the property. דסוף
סוף sof למפקא קאתיא *d'sof sof l'mafka ka-atya*, he feels she's going
to take it all away from me. So basically, here she brings
in this property, right, to the marriage. And he's going to say,
"Look, any time, any day she might wake up and decide she
doesn't like me and walk away." So therefore, what's that going to
mean? It's going to mean I'm going to lose all the benefit
of this property, right, because she's going to take it back with
her. So what I might as well do now is strip-mine the
property, get as much as I can from it without any concern
about the investment in the property, right? I'm not going to like
tend to it
and till it and so on. No! Why don't I just go
ahead and cut down all the trees, you know, strip-mine it, get
as much as I can from it right now, because any day
she might wake up and walk away? I might as well, you
know, grab what I can at this moment. And therefore, because... in
order not to allow him to encourage him to think that way,
we are going to say she can't do מיאון mi'un *miun*. That's
what בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* says. Does it work the other way
around too? Well, that's what בית הלל *Beis Hillel* is going to
respond. So okay, ובית הלל אמרי *u'Beis Hillel amri*, בית הלל *Beis
Hillel* says אדרבה *adaraba*, the opposite is the case. כיון דאמרת תמאן
*Kivan d'amart tmaen*, if you're giving her the power to be ממאן
mema'en *memaen*, אשבוחי משבח להו *ashvochei mashvach lehu*, he actually is going
to invest in the property, you know, and he's going to, you
know, fertilize it and plow and so on. Why? סבר *Savar*, because
he thinks, דאי לאו *d'ilav*, if I don't start showing that I
can be a responsible husband and invest in the property, ייעצו לה
קרוביה *yatz'u lah kroveha*, her relatives are going to advise her to
say, "Leave this guy! Look what he's doing to your property!" ומפקא
לה מיניה *u'mafka lah minei*, she'll take it away from you. So
because he knows that, you know, he's a little... his situation is
a little more precarious, tenuous, he's going to take אדרבה *adaraba* good
care of the property. Okay, so that's switching from sex to money.
All right, the only last thing is going to be politics. Let's
see if we can figure that out. Okay, rock and roll. So
רבא Rava אמר *Rava amar*, רבא אמר *Rava says* היינו טעמא דבית
שמאי *hainu taama d'Beis Shammai*, here's the reason of בית שמאי *Beis
Shammai*, שאין אדם טורח בסעודה ומפסידה *she-ein adam tore'ach b'seudah u'mafsidah*. We're
back to money. If you tell her, him, that if you say
she could be ממאן mema'en *memaen*, he's not going to want to
go ahead and have a wedding party because then I'm going to
spend all that money on the caterers or whatever and a whole
big wedding party, and then retroactively we won't have been married. So
therefore what?
It doesn't mean... the concern seems to be not that they'll do
נישואין *nisuin* without the party, but... The concern seems to be they
won't do נישואין. And again pointing to the fact that we want
this to progress to נישואין, there's a reason we made this rabbinic
institution, and therefore if he's not gonna want to invest in the
whole wedding party, you know, he's not gonna do נישואין. We don't
want to let that happen. And תוספות Tosafot says back תרווייהו ניחא
להו, tara-vaihu nicha lehu, you know what? Both of them are happy
to have a wedding party even if retroactively it was dissolved. Why?
כדי לגזולי קלה כיוצא אישה. kedei leguzlei kalah kaye-tzei ishah. People want
to have the standing in society that they're married. So even if
it'll retroactively even a nine-year-old girl. Even if retroactively it'll be
dissolved, for the time being, nobody minds to have a big wedding
party and to have this status even regardless of what's going to
happen in the future. Okay so fascinating different issues around why to
say that the woman might not be able to do מיאון, mi'un,
a woman, a girl, after
נישואין. Now... Right so that's what תוספות Tosafot points out. Even she'd
be even more desirous to do this. בית שמאי אומרים בבעל. Beit
Shammai omrim b'ba'al. Now, can you do מיאון mi'un, with the יבם?
yavam? Now what is the scenario with doing מיאון mi'un with יבם?
yavam? So I would think, I mean I'm you know and this
גמרא's Gemara gonna say later, but it's not the first thing the
גמרא's Gemara gonna say. The scenario is: she had this קידושי קטנה
kiddushei ketannah with ראובן, Reuven, right? Her father is dead etc. ראובן
Reuven dies and now she stands in front of שמעון Shimon to
do ייבום. yibum. So rather than doing ייבום yibum or חליצה, chalitzah,
she's gonna do her her מיאון mi'un now, a little late cause
ראובן's Reuven already dead, but okay, now she's gonna say 'you know
what? I never wanted to be married to your brother ראובן.' Reuven.
And then she can walk away without ייבום yibum or חליצה. chalitzah.
That would to me seem the most obvious case of can you
do מיאון mi'un with the brother-in-law? You didn't do it with your
husband, he died, can you still do it now that you're facing
a brother-in-law? But that's גמרא Gemara will get to that but it's
not the first interpretation it has of this idea of מיאון mi'un
with the brother-in-law. Let's take a look. בית שמאי אומרים בבעל. Beit
Shammai omrim b'ba'al. אמר רבי אושעיא, Amar Rabbi Oshaya, ממאנת למאמרו ואינה
ממאנת לזיקתו. mema'enet l'ma'amaro v'eina mema'enet l'zikato. So first let's explain the
last three words: אינה ממאנת לזיקתו eina mema'enet l'zikato is rejecting what
I just said. The brother died, she's standing in front of שמעון,
Shimon, her מיאון mi'un cannot be effective for her relationship, her זיקה
zikah to שמעון. Shimon. She didn't do it with ראובן, Reuven, she's
stuck with that זיקה zikah to שמעון, Shimon, her מיאון mi'un is
no longer meaningful. So what is her מיאון mi'un meaningful according to
בית הלל? למאמרו. L'ma'amaro. Remember, what can the brother-in-law do before ייבום?
yibum? Anybody remember what you do before ייבום yibum the rabbis want
you to do? They want you to do מאמר. ma'amar. Remember what
מאמר ma'amar is? It sounds like it's just words, but מאמר ma'amar
is actually
קידושין. kiddushin He actually says הרי את מקודשת לי בטבעת זו. harei
at mekudeshet li b'taba'at zo. For the outside perspective, it looks just
like normal קידושין. kiddushin The only reason it's not binding דאורייתא קידושין
d'oraita kiddushin is because this is a sister-in-law and the only thing
that's binding with a sister-in-law is ייבום yibum or חליצה. chalitzah. So
he actually gives her a ring. So ראובן Reuven died, now you
have רחל Rachel or whoever it is, the underage girl, right? So
רבקה Rivka I guess we'll make her three years old, okay.
So there it is and שמעון Shimon is going to come and
say הרי את מקודשת לי. harei at mekudeshet li. So it looks
so that's the same background as a normal case of מיאון, mi'un,
right? That you start with a קידושי קטנה kiddushei ketannah and now,
after שמעון Shimon has done this קידושין kiddushin with this minor where
there wasn't a father to marry her off, now שמעון Shimon wants
to now רבקה Rivka wants to come and do מיאון, mi'un okay.
She can do מיאון mi'un. once she's older, right? No, she does
מיאון mi'un until she's בת מצוה. bat mitzvah. She can do מצוה
mitzvah anytime until she's בת מצוה. bat mitzvah. Once she's בת מצוה
bat mitzvah it's too late. So he says before the מאמר ma'amar
she can't do... after the מאמר ma'amar she can do, but the
מיאון mi'un would only help to reverse the מאמר. ma'amar. Then she'd
be back in her status of needing חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, right? So
yeah, I know, it's surprising. You would think מיאון mi'un means she's
free. He says no, you got it wrong. The מיאון mi'un doesn't
help in terms of the זיקה zikah and the relationship with ראובן
Reuven and all that. All it means is that this new act
of קידושין that she might enter into with שמעון, Shimon, this מאמר,
ma'amar, that מיאון mi'un can work to reverse the מאמר ma'amar but
not to reverse everything because there's a זיקה. zikah. If there wasn't
מאמר ma'amar at all, מיאון mi'un is meaningless. And even if there
was מאמר ma'amar and מיאון, mi'un, it only gets you back to
square one. It does not mean that she's free, she still needs
חליצה chalitzah at that
stage, okay. So מיאון mi'un is a rabbinic injunction? Yeah, rabbinic. The
whole fact she was married was rabbinic, right. So that's why it
doesn't have any effect against זיקה zikah in that sense. What but
the whole זיקה zikah is rabbinic because she was never married to
ראובן. Reuven. Yeah, okay,
okay. Let's take a
look. בית שמאי אומרים Beit Shammai omrim, בבעל. אמר רבי אושעיא, Amar
Rabbi Oshaya, ממאנת למאמרו ואינה
ממאנת לזיקתו. mema'enet l'ma'amaro v'eina mema'enet l'zikato. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav
Chisda, מאי טעמא דרבי אושעיא? mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Oshaya? Why is רבי
אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya reading it that way? מאמר ma'amar for the following
reason, דמדעתה מצי עקרה. dim-da'atah matzi akra. מאמר ma'amar that is her
with her דעת, da'at, she has to willingly accept the כסף קידושין.
kessef kiddushin. And remember by the way קידושי קטנה kiddushei ketannah is
also with her דעת da'at when it's with the mother and the
brothers, not with the father. So since she is willingly entering into
that, she's empowered in that process. So she has the ability... ability
to uproot it with the מיאון. mi'un. מצי עקרא. matzi akra. זיקה
דעל כרחה, zika de'al korchah, the זיקה zika that she's not empowered
of, that she inherited from her, you know, because of a previous
marriage, she did not willingly enter into this relationship with שמעון, Shimon,
so לא מצי עקרא, lo matzi akra, her מיאון mi'un, should not
be meaningful for that. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ופרכינן
ביאה דעל כרחה, u'farchinan biah de'al korchah, how about ביאה? biah The
brother-in-law can do an act of ביאה biah with her, I mean
it's not against her will, but it's binding even if it's against
her will in terms of creating יבום. yibum. Okay, and מצי עקרא,
matzi akra, she can be עוקר. oker. Why can she be עוקר?
oker? Once there's יבום yibum you can't do anything. Because you might
remember that ביאת קטנה bi'as ketana or is like a מאמר ma'amar
or ביאת קטן, bi'as katan, right? Remember that, that ביאה biah only
works if it's an adult. What happens if they did יבום yibum
and she's a קטנה? ketana, That has the same effect as מאמר.
ma'amar. Okay, so she's it's דרבנן, derabbanan but she's it's not דאורייתא
de-Oraisa. binding. So if רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says you can do
a מיאון mi'un for a מאמר, ma'amar, he would also allow her
to do a מיאון mi'un after the brother-in-law had ביאה biah. with
her. Everybody get the scenario? ראובן Reuven died, she's a קטנה, ketana.
she had been married to ראובן, Reuven, this דרבנן derabbanan marriage. שמעון
Shimon now, either he gives her money and כסף קידושין kessef kiddushin
מאמר, ma'amar, or he has sex with her, which has the same
effect of ביאה biah because she's a קטנה. ketana, And there רבי
אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says she can do מיאון mi'un and that מיאון
mi'un. will reverse that act. She'll still now need חליצה, chalitza, okay,
again the מיאון mi'un won't help for the previous thing, but it'll
reverse the act that the brother-in-law did. So the גמרא Gemara is
saying ah, but you see it's reversing an act that she didn't
have control over. It's not just reversing the קידושין, the מאמר, ma'amar,
it's even reversing the ביאה. biah, So you see that רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya who's empowering her to do מיאון, mi'un? right, is is
this clear? Is there's a link between the power of מיאון mi'un,
and and דעת. da'as. Right. Yeah. But doesn't the ביאה biah, catapult
you into into יבום? yibum? Not when you're a קטנה, ketana okay.
So here's ראובן, Reuven, okay, yeah, קטנה's ketana. a separate category. And
here's his and in the context of יבום, yibum, let me draw
her small, I did. Okay, okay, so there you go. So she's
ראובן Reuven is married to to רבקה, Rivka, right? Then ראובן Reuven
dies. Okay, now here's his brother שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so first thing
you've got here is you've got a זיקה. zika. Okay, and that's
going to say you either have to do חליצה chalitza or יבום.
yibum. Okay, comes רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya and says her מאמר ma'amar
can't do anything to that זיקה. zika. She if she wanted that
זיקה zika is inherited, you know, sort of, you know, you know
through ראובן, Reuven, if she wanted to break that bond she had
to do it with ראובן. Reuven. So her מאמר ma'amar can't do
anything to that זיקה, zika, she's going to be stuck with that
זיקה. zika. What? מיאון. Me'un Excuse me, can't do anything to that
זיקה, zika, she's going to be stuck with it, she's either going
to, I'll give her a little dress, she's either going to have
to do, she's either going to have to have חליצה chalitza or
יבום yibum done. But now, if שמעון Shimon did something new with
her, he did מאמר, ma'amar, he did מאמר ma'amar or which equals
קידושין, or he even had sex, okay, ביאה, biah but it's ביאת
קטנה, bi'as ketana, okay, so all of these because it's a יבום
yibum context, right, all of these are basically דרבנן קידושין. derabbanan kiddushin.
ביאת קטנה bi'as ketana context. Right, right, so that's a type of
דרבנן קידושין, derabbanan kiddushin, you know, it's דרבנן derabbanan, binding because it's
a non not דאורייתא de-Oraisa binding. Okay, right. The reason מאמר ma'amar
in general is right, it's all דרבנן, derabbanan? meaning yeah, why is
it דרבנן? de-rabbanan There's no real even דאורייתא de-Oraisa here, he wasn't
really married, he gave her כסף קידושין kessef kiddushin because again, because
there's no father, she's a קטנה. ketana So this is all a
so he did a מאמר ma'amar or a ביאה, biah right, which
okay, that he did. So that's basically like קידושי קטנה. kiddushei ketana.
All right, so this along can come her מיאון, Me'un, I need
now a red marker but okay, whatever, along can come her מיאון
Me'un and her מיאון Me'un and her מיאון Me'un can eliminate that.
Okay, so there is מיאון למאמרו mi'un le-ma'amaro but there's not מיאון
לזיקתו. mi'un le-zikaso. This זיקה zika that she got through ראובן, Reuven,
that's still going to have to be dealt with and she's still
going to need חליצה chalitza for that. Okay, because she did not
if she needed to sever that bond she would have done it
with ראובן. Reuven. If he did something new and she's a קטנה
ketana still, right, she's still a קטנה Katanah and he did ביאה
bi'ah, or קידושין and that would have created this דרבנן קידושין derabbanan
kiddushin with her, that she can reverse through an act of מיאון.
Me'un But doesn't she just need to do מיאון Me'un at all?
Like let's say she decides she just want to do חליצה. chalitza.
חליצה chalitza should should supersede מיאון? Me'un, No, no, when you want
after מאמר, ma'amar, חליצה chalitza isn't enough, the Rabbis require there also
to be normally a גט. get, Here instead of a גט, get
they're allowing it to be מיאון, Me'un, right? But you still think
she'll need חליצה chalitza anyway, if you need חליצה chalitza to take
care of everything? Yeah, that's what I'm saying. You will need חליצה,
chalitza, but since there's מאמר ma'amar been done, you need to address
it and a way to address it is, and the point was
why does it work for this and not for this? So the
first answer is well, because she willingly got into this relationship. He
says no, she didn't necessarily willingly get into it. In the מאמר
ma'amar case she did, but in the ביאה case she didn't. So
you... So even though she didn't willingly get into it, why is
she still empowered to reverse this and not this? So the obvious
answer is that this—well, we'll see—this came from her husband, so the
מיאון Me'un would have to have been with her dead husband, whereas
this is new with שמעון, Shimon, so let's take a look at
the גמרא's answer. This is before— Yes. So ביאת קטנה, Bi'at Katanah,
she can then do מיאון, mi'un, and that will be enough according
to this to undo the ביאת קטנה. Bi'at Katanah. Right. Still needs
חליצה. Chalitzah. Exactly. Does—can she do חליצה קטנה Chalitzah Katanah or she
has to wait till she's old? No, that's a good point. If
you say that a קטנה Katanah, can't do חליצה, Chalitzah, then she'd
have to wait till she's older. That's a very good point. Okay.
So that might be the case, she has to wait— Yeah. Okay,
so yes, correct. So now the גמרא says like this: אלא ביאה
ומאמר דהוא קא עביד מצי עקרא. Ella bi'ah u-ma'amar di-hu ka-avid matzi
akra. ביאת מאמר Bi'at Ma'amar that שמעון Shimon did, so that's a
new relationship she entered into with שמעון, Shimon, and she's a קטנה,
Katanah. so for that relationship she's empowered to undermine it like she
would by normal קידושי קטנה, kiddushei Katanah, that the Rabbis empowered her
to undermine it. That's—that is a new relationship she entered into with
שמעון Shimon as a קטנה. ktanah, זיקה Zikah דרחמנא רמי עליה—זיקה that
she gets because the Torah imposed it. Now, it's not really Torah
because it only comes from ראובן Reuven and ראובן Reuven wasn't really
her husband. But in principle, the point is that's something she inherited,
the זיקה Zikah relationship through ראובן Reuven and it was about her
relationship to ראובן. Reuven. It didn't start with her relationship to שמעון.
Shimon. That לא מצי עקרא, lo matzi akra, that she cannot undermine.
Okay, so רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says that when we say she
can do מאמר, Ma'amar, it does not get her out of her
relationship with שמעון. Shimon. It only means if she enters into a
new relationship with שמעון, Shimon, something new is added—a קידושין or a
ביאה, whatever—מאמר Ma'amar can work for that. Okay, but it does not
mean that it can free her from the זיקה Zikah she inherited
from ראובן. Reuven. That's what רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says. Okay. עולא
אמר—now Ulla amar עולא Ulla says a much more straightforward thing. ממאנת
אף לזיקתו. Mena'enet af le-zikato. No, she can go ahead and even
though she did not say to ראובן Reuven "I don't want it"
and then ראובן Reuven died, she can say to שמעון Shimon "You
know what? I don't want you" and that—and that uproots the whole
relationship that she had originally with ראובן Reuven and she's free to
walk away, no חליצה, Chalitzah, she can just walk away. Okay, מאי
טעמא—מאי טעמא? נישואי קמאי קא עקרה. Nisu'ei kammai ka-akra. Because ultimately she
could have rejected ראובן. Reuven. So now she's basically—even though ראובן's Reuven
dead—she's undermining the original קידושין to ראובן, Reuven, the original relationship to
ראובן. Reuven. So she's vicarious ראובן. Reuven. Exactly. איתיביה רבא לעולא. Etiviyeh
Rava le-Ulla. Now רבא challenged עולא. Ulla. כל שיכולה למאן ולא מיאנה—any
Kol she-yecholah le-ma'en ve-lo me'anah woman who could do מיאון mi'un, and
didn't, meaning a woman who's in this scenario, צרתה חולצת ולא מתייבמת—her
tzarasah choletzet ve-lo mityabbemet sister, her co-wife does חליצה Chalitzah and not
ייבום. Yibbum. Okay, so basically what's the scenario? The scenario here is
that רבקה Rifkah is—okay, so we're going to remove this new thing,
that was רבי אושעיא, Rabbi Oshaya, okay, so fine, so she can
do here, right, she can do מיאון mi'un, on this relationship. That's
what we're saying now, she can do מיאון mi'un, and break that
relationship. Now let's say it just so happens that רבקה Rifkah is
actually שמעון's Shimon daughter here, okay? Right? Remember ערווה, ervah, צרת ערווה?
tzarat ervah? And let's say that he's got this other wife here,
okay, דבורה. Devorah. So is that a case of צרת ערווה? tzarat
ervah? Can he go ahead and do ייבום Yibbum with דבורה? Devorah?
So the answer is, well, דאורייתא yes, because רבקה Rifkah really isn't
a wife דאורייתא. So דאורייתא he really should be able to go
ahead and do ייבום Yibbum with דבורה. Devorah. Everybody with me here?
But דרבנן de-rabbanan it looks like צרת ערווה tzarat ervah so we
won't allow it, so we say do חליצה. Chalitzah. So that's what
it says. Anybody who could be ממאן mema'en and she wasn't ממאן
to ראובן, Reuven, she could have but she didn't, which means that
it's only a דרבנן de-rabbanan marriage. In this case where it's only
a דרבנן marriage because in theory she could have been ממאן to
ראובן, Reuven, then when he comes to the other wife he does
חליצה, Chalitzah, not ייבום. Yibbum. Okay, can't do ייבום Yibbum because she
didn't—wasn't ממאן and she's still in the picture. Okay, has to do
חליצה Chalitzah because דאורייתא she's not really a wife. So that's the
הלכה. So let's see what the question is. כל שיכולה למאן ולא
מיאנה, צרתה חולצת ולא מתייבמת. Kol she-yecholah le-ma'en ve-lo me'anah, tzarasah choletzet
ve-lo mityabbemet. ואמאי? Ve-amai? Why is this true? תמאן השתא ותעקרינהו לנישואי
קמאי ותתייבם צרתה. Tema'en hashta ve-takreinu le-nisu'ei kammai ve-tityabbem tzarasah. So if
you really, if רבקה Rifkah can really now do מיאון mi'un. and
uproot the whole relationship, right, if we're really saying that רבקה Rifkah
is able to do מיאון mi'un and make this all go away—רבקה,
Rifkah, you could make it all go away! Okay, so then why
do we say to שמעון Shimon do חליצה? Chalitzah? Why don't we
first say, "רבקה, Rifkah, do us a favor רבקה, Rifkah, do מיאון,"
mi'un which would then free שמעון Shimon to go ahead and do
ייבום Yibbum with the co-wife. Right? He's not going to do it,
right? So why don't—he's not going to do ייבום Yibbum with you,
you're his daughter, you're an ערווה, ervah, you're going to—not get—so why
not just make it easy for everybody, do מיאון, mi'un make it
all disappear and then he can—and then he can do ייבום. Yibbum.
Why don't we say that if she can really do מיאון mi'un.
and make it all go away? So the גמרא says— סוף ערווה
שאני. sof ervah shani. No, the סוף of an ערווה ervah is
different, דתניא רמי בר יחזקאל: de-tanya Rami bar Yechezkel: מיאון בבעל מותרת
לאביו, ביבם אסורה לאביו. mi'un be-ba'al muteret le-aviv, bi-yavam asurah le-aviv. So
here what he's taking is, because here's what's going to happen, I'll
tell you the basic answer then we'll fit in the words. He
basically says once ראובן Reuven dies and something has to be done
with her relationship with שמעון, Shimon, even if what has to be
done is she has to do מיאון, mi'un but basically, right, she
needs to do something to address this. So at that stage, meaning
at the moment of death, we are already going to look at
her as ראובן's Reuven wife, that's not going to go away. Why
is it not? Because since that's going to create a demand for
שמעון Shimon to do something, right, even if she goes ahead and
does something, and does the מיאון, mi'un and retroactively it all went
away, at the time when ראובן Reuven died before it retroactively became
undone, on January 1st when ראובן Reuven died, we said, "Ah, רבקה
Rifka was his wife, שמעון's Shimon got to do חליצה chalitzah or
she's got to do מיאון, mi'un, she's got to do something." And
then even if a week later she does מיאון, mi'un we say
retroactively it never happened, it didn't matter because on January 1st we
still looked at it as though it did happen. And therefore that
already defined her, you know, everybody's relationship. Where do we see that?
So the basic point is, meaning to say it more simply, even
when you retroactively make it all go away, it didn't... it hadn't
gone away at the time. So how must you are stuck with
the reality of what was created at that time even if afterwards
you've retroactively made it dissolved. Okay, so here's the case. In another
case, okay, simple case, simple. Okay, here he is. He's married to
this קטנה, ketannah? she does מיאון. mi'un, Okay, can she go ahead
and marry the father? She was never married to the guy, right?
If retroactively she was never married, she can marry the guy's father.
Okay, so ממילא mimmela if she can do מיאון mi'un, and she's
מותרת לאביו. muteret le-aviv. Okay, so here's יעקב. Yaakov. Okay, here's ראובן.
Reuven. Okay, so let's take a look at that. מיאון בבעל, mi'un
be-ba'al, she does מיאון mi'un with him, מותרת לאביו, muteret le-aviv, she
can now go ahead and marry יעקב Yaakov because she was never
married to him. However, ביבם, ראובן Reuven died, and here's שמעון, Shimon,
and now she does מיאון mi'un with שמעון, Shimon, okay, אסורה לאביו.
asurah le-aviv. She can't marry שמעון's Shimon father, she can't marry יעקב.
Yaakov. What's the difference? She did, right, what's the difference? Here she
also did מיאון. mi'un, So she was never married, uprooted the whole
thing, why can't she go ahead and marry יעקב? Yaakov? And the
reason is because once ראובן Reuven died and she needed to do
מיאון mi'un with שמעון, Shimon, that concretized the fact that she had
a real relationship with ראובן. Reuven. The fact that now we're demanding
something being done with שמעון Shimon says, "Oh, why are we demanding?
Because you were married to ראובן." Reuven. And then even after the
מיאון mi'un is done, the fact of, at least the impression or
the status of having been married to ראובן Reuven never goes away,
and she's forbidden to יעקב. Yaakov. So moving that over here, once
ראובן Reuven died, yes, if she did מיאון, mi'un it would completely
go away like it never happened. But once ראובן Reuven died and
now there's a need to do something with שמעון, Shimon, we've created
a reality about her marriage to ראובן. Reuven. We can no longer
say it never happened. And therefore even after she does מיאון mi'un
and makes it all go away, there's still a status of צרת
ערווה. tzarat ervah. Because at the time that ראובן Reuven died, she
was a צרת ערווה. tzarat ervah. So even when she made it
go away, that got somehow instantiated, that became a reality that cannot
completely disappear, and therefore even if she does מיאון, mi'un? she... there
still will be a... there still won't be allowed to do יבום
yibbum here because she'll still be a צרת ערווה. tzarat ervah. Yes.
So like, we said רבקה, Rifka, שמעון's Shimon daughter, right? And then,
you know, ראובן Reuven dies. So what does she, how does that
work exactly? What does she do? She goes to שמעון Shimon or
she goes to the בית דין Beit Din and like what does
she say? "I don't want..."? Yeah, so we'll talk about this. She
says she didn't want ראובן Reuven and she doesn't want שמעון. Shimon.
We'll get to that. But let's just finish this גופא. gufa. So
says: אלמא בשעת נפילה נראית ככלתו. alma bi-sh'at nefilah nirit ke-khallato. So
you see in the first case of רמי בר יחזקאל, Rami bar
Yechezkel, when ראובן Reuven died, she then became, it became somewhat instantiated,
you know, somewhat like a real thing that she was יעקב's Yaakov
daughter-in-law because now there's a need to do something with the brother-in-law.
So that, and that can't go away even after מיאון, mi'un even
if it gets retroactively undone, somewhat the remnant, you know, that status
still somewhat remains because it became a real thing. הכא נמי בשעת
נפילה נראית כצרת בתו. hacha nami bi-sh'at nefilah nirit ke-tzarat bito. Here
too, when he died, right, דבורה's Devorah still going to be a
צרת ערווה, tzarat ervah, and even if מיאון mi'un, is done and
retroactively it all disappears, it never really fully removes the status of
צרת ערווה. tzarat ervah. Okay, because that became a real thing because
it then translated into a responsibility to שמעון. Shimon. אמר רב, Amar
Rav, says רב, Rav מיאון בזה אסורה לזה. mi'un be-zeh asurah le-zeh.
Okay, so now we're dealing with against רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaiya. We're
dealing with the reality that she can do a מיאון mi'un. to
free herself from her relationship to the brother-in-law. Okay, so forget צרת
ערווה, tzarat ervah, we're back here, okay. ראובן Reuven dies, she didn't
do מיאון, mi'un she has a זיקה, zikah, her מיאון mi'un basically
frees her from her relationship to her brother-in-law. So comes along Michael
and says, who is she rejecting? Is she rejecting שמעון Shimon or
is she rejecting... and she's entitled to... There's two brothers-in-laws, right? Okay.
So, and she does מיאון mi'un with one. Does can she walk
away now, or does she have to do מיאון mi'un? with each
one? Right? Is it that now she's got all these זיקות zikas
and she's entitled to to do a מיאון mi'un on the זיקה
zika because ultimately it comes from this type of a relationship that
she could have done a מיאון? mi'un Or ultimately this is all
as some would say a surrogate for doing a מיאון mi'un on
ראובן? Reuben? And basically once she does one מיאון, mi'un she can
walk away from the whole thing. Is this different than a normal
case just because she's a קטנה? What do you mean? She wouldn't
have to do, she wouldn't have to do חליצה. chalitzah. Yeah, but
she's not doing חליצה, chalitzah, she's doing מיאון. mi'un So is מיאון
mian basically severing this one relationship, right? Well we'll see, maybe rabbinically
we would treat it like חליצה, chalitzah, but right now we're not
saying that. All right, well that's exactly the question. Is she doing
it if she's doing it to the original husband who's dead, then
it's exactly like חליצה. chalitzah. That's an interesting point too, maybe that's
the whole point of חליצה, chalitzah, exactly. All right, so let's take
a look. So, אמר רב, Amar Rav, מיאון בזה אסורה לזה. mi'un
b'zeh asurah l'zeh. If she did מיאון mian with with שמעון, Shimon,
she is forbidden to do ייבום yibbum with לוי. Levi. It basically
means that it works, it it dissolves the relationship completely. מידי דהוה
אבעלת הגט. Midi d'havah abaalas haget. Okay, it same would be if
she basically receives a גט get from שמעון, Shimon, which is sort
of like Dov's question. בעלת הגט לאו כיון דאיתסרה לחד איתסרה לכולהו?
Baalas haget, lav kivan d'it'asrah l'chad it'asrah l'kulu? If she got a
גט get from שמעון, Shimon, right, again a גט get now she's
in a זיקה zika status, but remember there's also a rabbinic גט
get for a זיקה zika status. So once she gets a גט
get from one brother, she's forbidden to all the brothers. הכא נמי
לא שנא. Hacha nami lo shana. So here too once she does
ייבום yibbum with one brother, she's disqualified from all the brothers. Now
what's not clear is what's not clear is can she walk away
or is she just אסור asur to the other brothers but maybe
now she's still not free yet? Okay. Yeah, that's not so clear
because the גט get. case is just an אסור asur case, but
nevertheless but anyway his basic point is you do it with one,
it's like it's complete, it's done it with all of them. ושמואל
אמר, U'Shmuel amar, let's just let's read. ושמואל אמר, U'Shmuel amar, מיאון
בזה מותרת לזה. mi'un b'zeh muteres l'zeh. No, even after doing מיאון
mian with שמעון, Shimon, she can go ahead and do ייבום yibbum
with לוי. Levi. ולא דמי לבעלת הגט, V'lo dami l'baalas haget, it's
not like a case of a גט. get, בעלת הגט הוא דקא
עביד בה. Baalas haget, hu d'ka avid bah. By גט, get the
man gave her the גט get and that somehow changed her status
and that was also an act that maybe he represented the brothers,
somehow that disqualifies her. הכא היא דקא עבדא ביה. Hacha, hee d'ka
avdah beih. She's basically doing it with him and so as he's
the one being sort of whose status is being changed, not her,
number one, which is an important concept, right? Normally it's always the
woman's status. Here, no, he's the one being rejected. דאמרה, D'amrah, and
she is saying לא רעינא בך, lo ravine becha, I don't want
you, buddy, I'm not interested in you, שמעון. Shimon. ולא צבינא בך,
v'lo tzevine becha, I don't want you, בך becha specifically, you שמעון
Shimon I don't like. הא בך ובאחרינא, Ha becha uv'acharina, you know,
לוי, Levi, he's a good guy, I wouldn't mind לוי. Levi. Okay?
So basically, this is, you know, so so here it says you
can reject one and remove the זיקה zika to one and still
maintain the זיקה zika to the other. And it's a nice point
that it's not her status that's being changed, which is normally how
we think חלוצה, chalutzah, גרושה, grushah, etc. They're the ones whose identity
and status or relationship is being affected. Is that like the official
phrase for the מיאון? mian Yes, we're going to see that. Yes,
it's exactly the language that they're going to use. We're going to
get to that. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, מיאון בזה מותרת
אפילו לו. mi'un b'zeh muteres afilu lo. You know what? If she
did מיאון mian just to one brother שמעון, Shimon, it's meaningless. She
can even go ahead and have ייבום yibbum with שמעון. Shimon. Need
the other brothers around? Or... Yeah, if there's other brothers, no, if
there's other brothers around. All right. Okay, so the גמרא says, לימא
כרבי אושעיא סבירא ליה? leima k'Rabbi Oshaya svira leih? Maybe it's like
רבי אושעיא, Rabbi Oshaya, right? רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says that the
מיאון mian is not meaningful for זיקה, zika, it's only meaningful if
there's like a מאמר. ma'amar. So maybe that's why he says if
she does מיאון with one brother it's meaningless. ואינה ממאנת לזיקתו. v'einah
mema'enes l'zikaso. גמרא says not necessarily. בחד יבם הכא נמי דמצי עקרה.
D'chad yavam, hacha nami d'matzei akrah. If there was just one brother,
he wouldn't pasken like רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. He would say if
it's one brother, she can do מיאון and it uproots the זיקה.
zika. אבל הכא בשני יבמים עסקינן. Aval hacha b'shnei yavmim askinan. But
here in two brothers-in-law we are dealing. דאין מיאון לחצי זיקה. D'ein
mi'un l'chatzi zika. You can't remove half the זיקה. zika. So basically
he's saying she inherited this double זיקה zika here, right? All of
that is is an extension of the זיקה zika of ראובן. Reuben.
If she wants to remove it, she's got to remove the whole
thing. Otherwise, you you can't remove half of a זיקה. zika. And
so she tries to remove this half, it doesn't work by itself.
All of it comes from ראובן. Reuben. So you either completely remove
it, you've got it all or you've got nothing, okay? You've got
to do it for each brother. Right, or she could maybe say
it collectively, I don't want any of you. Do they have to
be same people at one time? All right, exactly. Let's just get
to the two dots. So the גמרא says like this, רבין, Ravin,
okay, כי אתא רבין, ki ata Ravin, when רבין Ravin came, אמר
רבי יוחנן, amrah Rabbi Yochanan, he said in the name of רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, מיאון בזה מותרת לאחים. mi'un b'zeh muteres l'achim. If
she does מיאון with one, she can still have do it with
the brothers. That sounds like the idea that each brother is individual.
בלאו ובלאו. belo ubelo. But the other rabbis didn't agree to it.
מאן דהוא דלא? man dehu delo? Which of the previous opinions wouldn't
agree to it? אמר אביי רב, Amar Abaye Rav, so אביי Abaye
says רב doesn't agree because he says if you do מיאון with
one, you're forbidden on the other brothers, so clearly that doesn't agree
because here she says permitted on the other brothers. רבא אמר רבי
אושעיא. Rava amar Rabbi Oshaya. רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya doesn't agree because
רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says that there's no מיאון for זיקה zika
and this is being read that the reason it didn't work was
because there are multiple brothers, but presumably if there's one brother it
would work, and רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says it doesn't work even
with one brother. ואמרי לה רב אסי, Ve-amreilah Rav Assi, and some
say it's רב אסי, Rav Assi, you know, he's even disagreeing here
with רב אסי, Rav Assi, because what did רב אסי Rav Assi
say again? ומיאון בזה מותרת אפילו לו. U'mian bazeh muteres afilu lo.
So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying she's מותרת muteres to the
brothers, but she's not מותרת muteres to the guy himself. Okay, so
we have basically a whole range of positions. One is מיאון never
works for the זיקה, zika, the other is it does work for
the זיקה, zika, but then how? Does it work sort of like
a גט and you do מיאון with one brother and all of
them are sort of disqualified? Does she still need חליצה chalitza in
that case? It's not clear. The other is it works individually. It's
like each one she's got a זיקה zika that she could do
a מיאון to. And the third possibility is that it's either all
or nothing. You can't even do an individual זיקה. zika. You have
a whole collection of זיקות zikas and it's all inherited from your
first husband, so you either have to uproot everything or you've uprooted
nothing. Okay, so fascinating range of possibilities of what this מיאון means.
We will continue with this tomorrow. And so there's five brothers who
say all are collectively subject for that one brother? Exactly. And it
took 107 pages to finally learn that a צרה tzara is a
wife-in-law? That's pretty good.